C Minor Mass - Kyrie
This indicates the symmetric
fragments are caused by...
这说明对称碎片是由...
the passage of the fissioning nucleus
through an asymmetric cell...
分裂核穿过不对称细胞...
And now, ladies,
we'll have that last exercise again.
现在呢姑娘们 我们把最后的练习再做一遍
Margaret Bell, concentrate.
Margaret Bell 集中注意力
- 周末要来点特别的吗?
Anything for the weekend, sir?
- 不...谢谢你
No... thank you.
Ten shilling postal order, please.
请给我10先令的邮政汇票 谢谢
飞机在广岛投下了炸弹
The plane that dropped the bomb
on Hiroshima
该飞机是以飞行员的母亲命名的...
was named for the pilot's mother...
Enola Gay Tibbets,
Enola Gay Tibbets
那颗炸弹 也就是她腹中的罪孽..
and the bomb -
that obscenity in her belly...
取名为"小男孩"
they christened it Little Boy.
Was Mrs Tibbets proud of her little
boy that day?
Tibbets太太那天是否为她的小男孩感到自豪?
向爷爷道晚安
Say good night to Grandpa.
晚安Bob 好好睡
Good night, Bob. Sleep tight.
He had a hat and everything.
他戴着帽子 行头齐备
- 那证件呢?
- 看他戴着帽子 我就没想着要问
What about identification? I
didn't think to ask - with the hat.
You usually get a receipt
when the meter's empty.
燃气罐空了通常会给收据
He said I'd get one in the post.
Ah! Ah.
他说给我寄回来
我得为这个损失负责吗?
Will I be liable for the loss?
应该不会吧
Oh, I wouldn't have thought so.
Gas board
are pretty good about
this sort of thing.
燃气公司常处理这种事
这样 如果没别的事的话
Well, if there's nothing else.
抓到他的机会不大吧?
Don't suppose there'll be much
chance of you catching him,
what with these post offices
getting knocked off.
你看邮局都遭袭了
Well, we'll certainly do our best.
我们尽力而为吧
我叫Bright 总警司Bright
My name is Bright.
Chief Superintendent Bright.
Firstly, I would just like
to express my gratitude
首先我想感谢
to Detective Inspector Thursday
for holding the fort so admirably
Thursday督察在我未到职期间
多有所劳
pending my arrival.
第二...
Secondly...
Secondly, you should
be aware that I
第二 我先丑话说在前头
am putting this
station on notice.
我不想说前任长官的是非
I do not propose
to speak ill of my predecessor,
但以后若不守规矩肆意妄为的话
but where there are breaches
of procedure or Spanish practices,
你们别怪我翻脸
you will find me a horse
of a very different colour.
这就是说 我希望大家一切从零开始
That said, I want you to regard
my appointment as a tabula rasa.
一切重头来过
A clean slate.
你们公平待我 我也报之以公平
You play fair by me,
then I will play fair by you.
干活吧
Carry on.
吃葡萄不吐葡萄皮
Around and around the rugged rock
the ragged rascal ran.
- 干嘛
- 有点低级吧?
What?
Well, that's a bit cheap, isn't it?
看起来跟你像是一路人啊
从头开始 来姨妈啊
He'd be right up your street,
I suppose. Tabula wasa. My Aunt Flo.
- 如果你没事做我可以给你点 Jakes
If you've no work, Jakes,
some will be found for you.
- 知道了
Sir.
Don't let them get a rise.
别让他们得逞
- 没什么
- 这叫不服从
It's nothing.
Insubordination's what it is.
By proxy. You're my bagman.
你是我的人 算我的得力助手
I know what's going
round the canteen. Job
我知道餐厅里的事
should have gone to a
detective sergeant.
按理说接案子的应该是警长
Well, it didn't. It went to you.
但是却让你办了
You're here on merit.
你是凭本事进来的
你是不知道你的形象是吧
好歹找时间熨一下啊
Not that you'd know. You might
have found time to run an iron.
那衬衫看着像你的睡衣
That shirt looks
as though you slept in it.
First impressions, Morse.
第一印象很重要的 Morse
好了...
Right...
Sudden death on Southmoor Road.
Uniform just wants the all-clear.
Southmoor街有一件猝死案
巡警想让人去排除其他嫌疑
谢谢长官
Thank you, sir.
你应该在门口看着的不是吗?
You're meant to be on the door.
Sorry. I just come off nights.
抱歉 我夜班翻班
It's playing havoc with my...
有点不舒服...
I think I can live without the
details of your digestive timetable.
我对你的消化问题不感兴趣 不用告诉我
- 你是谁?
Who are you?
I could have just wandered in
- 我很可能是进来盗窃的
for a bit of housebreaking.
你要这么说话的话就让我看看你的证件
If you're gonna be like that, let's
see some identification, matey.
快点
Sharpish.
Oh. YOU'RE Morse.
你就是Morse啊
Strange.
Strange(奇怪)
What is? I am.
- 什么是奇怪?
- 我是
Me.
我
我名字 Jim Strange
My name. Jim Strange.
The... sawbones is here
if you wanted a word.
你要是想问话的话医生在这
It's all right. You can look.
没事 你可以接受的
没什么吓人的 至少没血
Nothing here to frighten the horses.
No blood, leastways.
What's the er...
什么...
根据我多年的医学经验判断应该是心脏病
My extensively educated medical
guess would be a heart attack.
Young, isn't she?
这么年轻?
你得问问她的医生才知道
You'll need to run her GP to ground,
但是地高辛是治疗心脏疾病的
but Digoxin would suggest
a heart defect of some sort.
Time of death?
死亡时间?
根据她的身体僵直状态
Rigor completely passed.
推测死亡时间大约在周六12点之前
So some time
before noon on Saturday.
- 她是谁?
- Margaret Bell
Do we know who she was?
Margaret Bell.
听Byng小姐介绍 她家在Rhodesia
Her family's in Rhodesia,
according to Miss Byng.
Landlady. She's next door at the
是房东 这会在隔壁
minute, having a cuppa.
For the shock.
喝茶压惊
还有两个姑娘住在这
Two other girls live here
but they went away Friday morning
for a week in Rhyl.
但周五早上离开 去Rhyl待一个星期
That's as far as you've got, is it?
No. Student, I'd say.
- 你就找到这些信息是吗?
- 还有 她是学生
某个学院的
One of the er... colleges.
Beaufort学院的颜色 这是Beaufort的颜色
These are Beaufort colours
and it's unlikely
she'd have been an
undergrad there.
可她不可能是那个学院的学生
Why not?
Because they don't admit women.
- 为什么
- 因为他们不收女生
More likely secretarial college.
- 更像是秘书学院
- 我已经查过她的钱包了
I've already had a go through
her purse.
30先令和一只没用过的避孕套
30 bob and a French letter. Unused.
Hope springs eternal
in the human breast,
希望春天永驻心田
Man never is,
but always to be blest...
人类从未如此 但一直有被赐福...
她医生那有消息就告诉我好吗 Morse?
Keep me posted on the GP, Morse,
will you?
OK, let's go.
我们走
Good boy, Bobby.
好孩子 Bobby
好棒啊!
There you go!
你喜欢玩这个吗? 喜欢开车吗?
Did you like that?
Did you like driving?
Yes.
是啊
别生气 我就是经过
Don't be cross. I was just passing.
别胡说了 Pamela 你知道你不是
Don't talk rot, Pamela.
You know perfectly well you weren't.
我带了几件干净的换洗衣服
I brought a few changes.
They're all clean.
That's very good of you.
You needn't have.
谢谢你的好意 你不用麻烦
I'm expecting Frank home any minute,
for lunch.
我在等Frank回家吃午饭
我可以做野餐 Bobby可以帮我 是不是呀?
I could make junket.
Bobby could help me, couldn't you?
真的 你不能老这样
Honestly, you can't keep doing this.
Five post offices knocked over
in the last two months, sir.
过去两个月有5间邮局被窃
全都在半径为20英里的范围内
All within a 20-mile radius.
None on our ground, though?
Not as yet.
- 但是没发生在我们的地盘上?
- 暂时还没
但是也该有所准备 长官
But as well to be prepared, sir.
I'd prefer you concentrated
on this gas meter menace.
我希望你着重解决燃气表的事
有一个受害人是
It transpires one
of his victims is
great-aunt to the Assistant
Chief Constable.
助理警察局长的姨婆
我答应说我们会尽快破案
I promised we'd roll out
the silver service, rapid result.
好的 长官
Right, sir.
- 如果没别的事儿的话...
- 还有一件事儿
Well, if there's nothing else,
I'll - There is one other matter.
I understand you've a detective
constable acting as bagman.
我知道你有个警员是你的助手
Morse, sir. Good man.
他叫Morse 长官 人很好
人都是好人Thursday
They're all good men,
Thursday, but the
rank system is there
for a purpose.
但是论资排辈是有道理的
Bagman is a detective sergeant's
post.
- 助手是警长的职位
He's an exceptional officer, sir.
- 他是特例 长官
还没当两年警察就被调到刑警
Barely two years in uniform
before being transferred to CID.
你也许当宝 可别人不知道怎么用他
Which, you may rely, means
no-one knew what to do with him.
Or his talents lay elsewhere.
或者说他的聪明在别的地方
A grammar scholarship and a
failed degree might impress some...
有语法学校的奖学金和没拿到学位
也许让人印象深刻
但事实说明他缺乏经验
..but the truth of it is he lacks
experience.
I'm bringing him on.
我会带他的
我希望我们别一开始就闹僵了 Thursday
I'd as soon we didn't
get off on the wrong foot, Thursday.
- 我也不希望
Likewise, sir.
On your own recognisance.
- 那你自己判断
试用一段时间
And for a probationary period only.
他如果惹出一点点麻烦 就让他回去值勤
The first hint of a hullaballoo,
he'll be returned to general duties.
好的
Sir.
我们在Bell小姐屋子里发现一瓶地高辛
In Miss Bell's room,
we found a bottle of Digoxin,
which is a derivative of digitalis.
是洋地黄的一种衍生物
我觉得是个很危险的东西啊?
Quite dangerous, I'd have thought.
Prentice医生?
Doctor Prentice?
是的 很致命的药
Ah, yes, quite lethal.
It's not called "deadly nightshade"
for nothing.
茄属植物毒王可不是浪得虚名
但有时候
But for certain cases,
比如Margaret先天的心脏缺陷
such as Margaret's congenital heart
weakness,
这个药物其实可以促进收缩加强心肌功能
it can actually help the heart
muscle contract and do its work.
Which is why I have to say I am
surprised.
这就是为什么我觉得惊讶
Surprised?
- 惊讶?
A heart attack.
- 心脏病发作
如果她在吃药 那...
If she was taking her medication,
then...
- 聆讯的时候会传唤我吧?
- 当然
You will notify me
as to the inquest? Of course.
Hello, old girl.
Lunch won't be long.
你好 亲爱的
- 午餐马上就好了
- 等等再吃
Oh, hang lunch.
Not now, Frank, please.
I'm getting a head...
别 Frank 我有点儿头疼...
- 周末吧
- 好
Perhaps at the weekend. Mm.
Pamela来了 在准备野餐
Pamela is here, making junket,
if you please.
我希望她不要老这么不请自来
I do wish she wouldn't just drop by.
Maybe you can talk to her.
- 你跟她谈谈好吗
Yes, all right. If you like.
- 好的 如果你想的话
Said you'd run her into town
when you were back from the surgery.
就说你看完病人才回来 可以带她回城
Perhaps that would be a good time
to raise it.
这个时候聊比较好
我上次见她的时候把围巾给她了
I lent her my scarf the last time
I saw her.
When did you see her last, Denis?
最后一次见她是什么时候 Denis?
我们说好周五一起出去的 但是...
We were meant to go out Friday
but she erm...
..couldn't make it.
她没来
给 抽根烟吧 镇定一下
Here. Have a smoke.
Steady your nerves.
谢谢 我不抽烟
No, thanks. I don't.
What about Miss Bell? Did she smoke?
Bell小姐呢? 她抽吗?
No.
不抽吧
I don't think so.
我认为不抽
Your...
你的...
Er...
和Bell小姐... 是...
With Miss Bell. That was a...
..full relationship?
- 关系有多深?
- 她不是那种女孩
She wasn't that sort of girl.
What sort of girl was she?
Nice.
- 她是哪种?
- 好女孩
She wouldn't laugh at you
or make you feel small
她不会因为你穷
就嘲笑你或者让你觉得渺小
just cos you've not had it all
handed to you on a plate.
奖学金?
A scholarship?
There's no shame in that.
这可不丢人
Not many girls here would go with
a bloke who darns his own cuffs.
在这 没多少姑娘会和
自己补袖口的男孩在一起
God knows
what she was doing with me.
天知道她为什么跟我在一起
好了 来猜猜今天吃啥
Right, what have we got today?
周一芝士和酸黄瓜 周二午餐肉
Monday, cheese and pickle.
Tuesday, luncheon meat.
别扫兴 期待才是乐趣所在
Don't ruin it.
Anticipation's half the fun.
Cheese and pickle! What do you know?
芝士和酸黄瓜! 没猜到吧?
所以那个猝死案...
So, this sudden death...
Margaret Bell. 20 years old.
Margaret Bell 20岁
就读秘书学院
At secretarial school.
- 看起来像自然死亡
- "看起来像"?
Looks to be natural causes.
"Looks to be"?
She had a heart condition
but her GP said she
她心脏有问题 但是她医生说
她吃了药不该还犯病的
should have been fine
with her medication.
Maybe she forgot.
Maybe. But she'd had someone there.
- 或许忘了呢
- 有可能 但她死的时候屋里有别人
A boyfriend. No law against it.
This
- 那就是男朋友 这又不犯法
不是她男朋友 因为他不抽烟
isn't her steady.
He doesn't smoke.
窗户外面茶碟里有些烟头
There were some cigarettes
in a saucer on the window ledge.
星期五晚上下了雨 但茶碟是干的
It rained Friday evening,
but the saucer was dry.
- DeBryn医生没觉得有啥蹊跷吧?
Dr DeBryn doesn't anticipate
anything untoward?
No, but...
- 没有 但是...
You're kicking your heels. Turn
your mind to these gas meter jobs.
别没事找事 先想想那个燃气表的案子
Get a decent collar or two
under your belt.
好歹先破一两个案子再说
还有 和Bright先生说话注意着点
Mind how you go with Mr Bright.
他特别注重规章制度什么的
He looks to be a stickler for rules
and regs.
It's my card he's after marking,
not yours.
他是想对我指手画脚 不是你
Keep your head down and
your nose clean.
所以你做事低调点 尾巴夹紧
多放点精力在警务上 知道吗?
Concentrate on your police work.
All right?
"Going to the Moonlight Rooms
with you know who."
"一起去Moonlight Rooms 知名不具"
- 知道她指谁吗?
Any idea who that might be?
- 我想可能是Derek
I think it may be Derek.
She spoke about some man called
Derek. Works in the post office.
她提到过一个叫Derek在邮局工作的人
Thanks very much.
- 回见
- 谢谢
Her name is Margaret Bell.
She died on Friday.
她叫Margaret Bell 星期五死了
我只想知道你是否认识她
I just wondered if you knew her.
Can't say I knew her well.
Only to say hello to.
不太熟 点头之交
是吗? 她的速记本里写着
Really? She'd written
in her shorthand notebook
她跟"知名不具"周五要在Moonlight Rooms见面
that she was meeting "you know who"
at the Moonlight Rooms Friday,
她朋友觉得"知名不具"指的是你
and her friends thought
"you know who" referred to... you.
我不知道他们为什么这么觉得
I don't know why they think that.
我在那里见到过她几次 只能这么说
I might've said I'd see her there
some time, if I was going.
But as it was, I ended up
down the Legion, on Edgecombe Road.
但实际上我去的是Edgecombe路上的英国皇家军团
英国皇家军团? 不会很无聊吗?
The Legion?
That's a bit dull, isn't it?
- 去找我爹 他是英国皇家军团的
I go for the old man. He's a member.
So you didn't meet Margaret later?
- 所以你后来没去见Margaret?
Look, you asked me if I'd seen her,
I said no.
听着 你问我见过她没 我说了没有
Did you know she had a boyfriend?
你知道她男友吗?
谁啊? 大学生?
Who's that, then? A college boy?
That's what they come here
for, isn't it, secretaries?
秘书们来这不就是图这个吗?
给自己找个老公
Pick themselves up a husband.
找到了可是美好生活每一天啊
Some bluer prospect
if they can get it.
I don't think I said she was a
secretary.
- 我没说她是秘书吧
- 我猜到的
The impression I got.
Cheerio, Wally.
再见 Wally
Morning, love. Mr Clark.
- 早上好亲爱的
- Clark先生
Derek
Derek.
Afternoon, Miss. Just the regular?
下午好 小姐 和平时一样吗?
- 是的
- 没什么事吧 长官?
Please.
Everything all right, Officer?
He's not in any trouble, is he?
- 他没惹什么麻烦吧?
Just a routine inquiry, Mr Clark.
- 就是例行询问 Clark先生
He's a good lad. I'm sure.
- 他是好孩子
- 是的
谢谢
Thank you.
We've er... We've got the poster up.
我们...我们把海报贴出来了
Nixon警员送来的 真是个不错的年轻人
PC Nixon dropped it round.
Very nice young man, he is.
It's a worry, though.
Kidlington. That's only up the road.
但是让人担心啊 Kidlington可就在路的那一头
你要是看见外面有人行踪可疑...
If you see anyone acting suspiciously
or loitering outside...
你是说踩点?
Casing the place, you mean?
是的 这几次抢劫都是
Yeah, the robberies
seem to have been
事先摸过底的样子
conducted with some
foreknowledge.
Cash deliveries and what have you.
不管是现金交收还是啥的
Anyone you're not sure
of, just give the
只要觉得谁行踪可疑 给警局打电话
station a call and we'll
have someone round.
我们会派人过来的
What was all that about?
这是怎么回事?
Nothing. Some girl I half know died.
没什么 我一个不太熟的女孩死了
- 死了? 怎么死的
- 我怎么知道 就是死了
Died? What of?
How do I know? Just died.
他们和每个认识她的人都要谈一谈
They're talking to everyone
who knew her.
Mr Truby from regional's coming by
for eight.
分区的Truby先生8点前会来
- 我想让你带他过一下季报
I want you
to take him through the quarterlies.
You know I'm out Mondays.
- 你知道我周一要出去
你每天晚上都出去 还有几毛钱剩下啊你
You're out every night.
It's a wonder you've any money left.
Jesus.
天呐
Hey. I won't have language.
Not in this house.
喂 在家说话注意点
If your mother
could see you carrying on...
要是你妈妈知道你...
可她不知道啊 是吧? 她死了
She can't, though, can she?
She's dead.
她死了 就剩下你和我...
She's dead and it's just you and me
and...
..fish fingers, pension books...
炸鱼条和退休金
..world without end.
还有这个无休止的世界
哈利他妈的路亚
Halle-bloody-lujah.
我已经尽力了 你想要什么?
I've done my best. What do you want?
我想要别的
Something else.
Something more.
其他的
而不是这个
Not this.
-  知道他身份吗?
-  身上没有钱包 长官
Do we know who he was?
No wallet on him, sir.
But the car's registered
to a Dr Cartwright.
但是车是注册在Cartwright医生名下的
他和Prentice医生在Florence Park有一个诊所
Got a practice in Florence Park
with a Dr Prentice.
- Prentice?
- 是啊 怎么了?
Prentice? Yeah. Why?
I was there yesterday.
我昨天在那儿
He's the GP in that sudden death -
Margaret Bell.
他是Margaret Bell的医生
Killed some time
between nine and midnight.
昨晚九点至十二点间被杀
Single shot. Weapon discharged
from over by the door there.
一枪致命 那边门旁开的枪
Bullet entered the skull
half an inch above the...
子弹从脑壳上方半英吋...
left point of the supraorbital
ridge...
眉骨摄入...
..and went on its merry way
射出点在中部
to exit at about the
median point of the
左边枕骨缝合线中部射出
left parietal occipital
suture line.
然后 子弹就在这里
And... Yes. And end up...
在它该在的地方
Hey, as it were...
presto.
说在就在
No wallet you say? Robbery, then.
Possibly, sir.
- 你说没有钱包? 那是抢劫吧
- 有可能 长官
In any event, I think
it best Sergeant Jakes
不管怎么样 我希望这段时间
由Jakes警长负责事故调查科
assume management of
the incident room.
Morse探员是我的助手 长官
DC Morse is my bagman, sir.
Morse may remain as your driver
and aide de camp,
Morse可以继续当你的司机兼私人助理
但像这样的案子需要一个
but a case such as
this requires an
有经验或是更高级别的长官
officer of experience
or senior rank
来负责
to coordinate the inquiry.
我看你们重点关注的是这辆自行车?
You're giving primary
consideration to
this bicycle, I take it?
Quite right.
挺好
Sir. I recall a not dissimilar case
in Freetown.
- 是的
- 我记得Freetown有个类似的案子
The usual mammy-palaver.
又是个黑人妇女瞎扯的案子
But the killer left his bicycle
at the scene.
但是杀人犯把自行车留在了现场
应该可以从车号追查到车主
You should be able to trace
its owner from the frame number.
Really? In Oxford?
是吗? 在牛津?
Morse的意思是
What Morse means to
say, sir, is that
这里的自行车比英国其他地方
there's probably more
cycles hereabouts
than anywhere in the country.
都要多一些
Bikes get lost, borrowed... stolen.
Right?
遗失啊 借的或者偷来的车 对吧?
是的 长官
Yes, sir.
But if the registered
owner isn't
但是我们要找的车主是个
left-handed, then he's
probably not our man.
是个左撇子
Left-handed?
左撇子?
正如您所见 您可以仔细看看
As you'd have noticed, given the
opportunity to examine it yourself,
前后刹车缆线都左右换过了
the front and rear brake cables
have been swapped over.
He'll also be an older man,
and of limited means, possibly.
而且可能是个上了年纪 经济不富裕的人
- 你怎么知道的?
- 这车是老古董
How did you get to that, then?
Well, the bike's ancient.
但保养得很精心 所以说明他很节俭
But well maintained. Which points
to thrift, I'd have thought.
- 再和粗心联系起来...
Taken together with evidence
of absent-mindedness...
- 粗心?
What evidence?
He sometimes forgets
to wear his bicycle clip, sir.
他有时候会忘记带上骑自行车用的裤管夹
There are scraps of material
torn from his trousers in the gears.
车轮里有裤管上撕扯下来的布料
One a cavalry twill,
the other's a linen. Both black.
有马裤呢 还有亚麻 都是黑色的
所以他有穿深色衣物习惯
He wears subfusc as a matter of
habit.
A don, then? Hm?
所以是学校的老师?
Perhaps, sir. But I think,
given the limited means...
有可能 长官 但是考虑到他经济不富裕...
我觉得可能是神职人员
we are looking
for a man of the cloth.
A vicar shooting somebody in a lav?
你说在厕所里杀人的是牧师?
I hope you'll eliminate
known criminals
我希望你去打搅神职人员前
先排除下累犯 Thursday
from your inquiries
first, Thursday,
before troubling any clergymen,
what?
Really, Constable Morse...
you should be on the halls.
真的 Morse警员...你该在局里待着
我就是这么提醒你的吗?
That minding how you go, is it?
你和Cartwright医生一起行医多久了?
How long had you and Dr Cartwright
been in practice together?
Uh, 18 months.
18个月
We were juniors together
at the Radcliffe.
我们都是Radcliffe医院的新人
你觉得有什么人可能会想伤害他吗?
Is there anyone you can think of
who would wish to harm him?
Anyone with whom he's had a falling
out?
他跟什么人起过争执吗?
没有
No, not a soul.
Cartwright医生戴着婚戒
Dr Cartwright wore a wedding band,
sir.
I presume he was married.
我想他结婚了
是的 他太太叫Helen....
Yes, a girl called Helen. Uh...
他们住在Cumnor附近的Sloan大宅
They live at Sloan House by Cumnor.
Place belongs to her father,
Edmund Sloan.
房子是她父亲Edmund Sloan的
他是Beaufort的物理系教授
He's professor of physics
at Beaufort.
Edmumd Sloan爵士 研究原子的那位?
Sir Edmumd Sloan, the atom man?
Yes, that's right.
没错
你们不反对的话 我想把这件事情告诉他
I'd like to put him in the picture,
unless you have any objection.
Coincidence, don't you think?
你不觉得这很巧吗?
昨天我们发现Margaret Bell死了
Yesterday we find Margaret Bell dead
今天她医生的搭档就被枪杀
and today the partner of her GP
is found shot dead.
猝死就是猝死
Sudden death's sudden death.
Just cos it's
a pretty girl doesn't
make it murder.
不能因为死的人漂亮就成了谋杀了
I didn't say it was.
我没说是谋杀
Cartwright's been shot,
not Prentice.
Cartwright被枪杀 不是Prentice
What was all that
about with Mr Bright, earlier?
前面和Bright那是怎么回事?
我知道你聪明
I know you've a brain on you,
but as far as he's concerned,
a bit more of the humble policeman
但他要的不过是谦虚警员
and a bit less of
the great detective
和锋芒不露的探员
would go down a
whole lot easier.
What's all this about?
这是怎么了?
Perhaps you should sit down,
Mrs Cartwright.
你先坐下说吧 Cartwright太太
Oughtn't we to wait for Sir Edmund?
我们不要等Edmund爵士吗?
Wait for Daddy for what?
等爸爸做什么?
我们有些不幸的消息要告诉你们
I'm afraid
I have some very grave news for you.
Who is it, Helen? The police.
- Helen 这是谁?
- 警察
Um... My little sister. Mrs Walters.
这是我妹妹 Walters太太
- 是爸爸吗?
- 不是 女士
Is it... Daddy? No, madam.
是你的丈夫 Cartwright太太
It concerns your husband,
Mrs Cartwright.
I'm sorry to tell
you his body was
很遗憾地告诉你这个
discovered this
morning at Godstow.
今天早上我们在Godstow发现了他的尸体
他被枪杀了
He'd been shot.
My God.
天呐
Helen 我...
Helen, I...
天呐 快扶着她!
Oh, my God! Somebody catch her!
没事的 是癫痫 她一会就会好的
It's all right. It's a seizure.
She'll be all right in a minute.
We just have to keep talking to her.
Pamela?
一直和她说话就好了 Pamela?
Pamela 好姑娘 我们都在这
Pamela, good girl.
We're all here.
这就对了 好姑娘
That's it. Good girl.
Keep talking to her.
Just breathe. Good girl.
继续和她说话 呼吸 好姑娘
All right. Well done.
好了 做得很好
That's it.
就这样
It's all right.
这就对了
我们需要有人去辨认尸体
We'll be needing someone
to identify the body.
- 如果我能代表他们家去的话...
If I can spare the family...
Have you known them long?
- 你认识他们很久吗?
Four years or so.
四年多
通过Frank认识的
Through Frank.
In Lady Sloan's last illness,
she was treated at the Radcliffe.
Sloan女士上次发病的时候
是在Radcliffe接受治疗的
That's how Frank
got to know the family.
Frank就是在那认识她们的
All was well at home?
家里关系还好吧?
鞋子舒不舒服只有脚知道
Well, only the wearer knows
where the shoe pinches.
Hm.
但应该是没事的
But absolutely, I'd say.
Helen人很好
Helen's a wonderful girl.
Would you know if
there's any firearms
Cartwright太太
请问你们家中是否有武器?
kept on the premises,
Mrs Cartwright?
Oh...
妈妈有把手枪
Mother had a pistol.
For vermin. Squirrels and the like.
是用来防备歹徒和松鼠之类的
好几年没见过了
I haven't seen it in years.
- Helen
- 他走了
Helen. He's gone.
他走了
He's gone.
- 我知道 我知道
- 爸爸
I know, I know. Daddy.
Shh.
以前在这的 和一盒子弹放在一起的
It was here.
Together with a box of ammunition.
- 你上次是什么时候看到它的?
- 不记得了 很多年没开过这个抽屉了
When did you last see it? I doubt
I've opened this drawer in years.
Frank may have borrowed it
for something.
Frank可能拿去用了
Can you think of anyone
who bore him any ill will?
你觉得有谁会想致他于死地吗?
Some disgruntled patient or...
比如心怀不满的病人..
No. He had perfect bedside manner.
- 不 他对病人的态度非常好
No problems with the practice?
- 诊所也没问题?
Did he get on well with Dr Prentice?
As far as I'm aware.
- 他和Prentice医生处得好吗?
- 据我所知还不错
我知道你要和我们每个人进行谈话
I know you need to speak
to all of us,
但和Pamela谈的时候能否温柔点
but if you could go gently
with Pamela.
She's been through a lot.
她不好受
因为她丈夫Gerald也过世了
Gerald, her husband, died.
我怕这一切让她想起过去
I'm afraid
this will have brought it all back.
- 他怎么死的?
- 车祸
What happened to him?
Car crash.
The other fellow's fault. Drink.
司机酒后驾车
When was this?
Two, two-and-a-half years ago.
- 什么时候的事?
- 两年半前吧
Made the papers, I believe.
- 估计上报纸了
Had they been long married?
- 他们结婚时间长吗?
Just back from honeymoon.
刚度蜜月回来
闪婚的
Whirlwind romance.
他是个她在伦敦帝国化学工业公司认识的年轻人
He was some young chap
she'd met at ICI in London.
She had a job in the typing pool.
她是个打字员
Registry office. None of us invited,
of course.
结婚的时候 我们都没有被邀请
I'm afraid we'd rather lost touch.
我宁愿我们失去联系
With Pamela's illness...
因为Pamela的病...
..things have not always been easy
between us.
我们的关系搞得有点僵
If you could be careful with her.
Of course, sir.
- 所以还请说话小心措辞
- 好的 爵士
Hang on. See what the sister's
got to say when she comes to.
你在这转转 等她妹妹好点
看看她有什么要说
- 好的
Right.
Just the who, what,
where and when of it
- 只要知道时间 地点 人物和内容就行
目前我们只要了解这些
. That's all we're after
for the time being.
I'll get a car to run
you and Mrs Cartwright
我会叫车来接你和Cartwright太太
down to the mortuary
for the formal ID.
去停尸房认尸
她知道她先生在Godstow做什么吗?
Did she know what her husband
was doing at Godstow?
明显是个钓鱼爱好者
Keen angler, apparently.
Evenings he was on call,
he'd go fishing after work.
晚上值班后他会去钓鱼
本来是没什么问题 但现在不是钓鱼季
Which is all right as far as
it goes, but it's closed season.
Whatever her husband
was doing at
不管他昨晚在Godstow做什么
Godstow last night,
it wasn't fishing.
肯定不是钓鱼
你是谁?
Who are you?
Constable Morse.
Morse警员
I've seen you before.
我以前见过你
Cowley Parade, yesterday.
昨天在Cowley Parade
Where's Bobby? My little boy.
Bobby呢? 我儿子
Helen
Helen.
I'm so sorry.
我很遗憾
我觉得在这种时候
I don't think it's fair
for Helen to have to
cope with Bobby on top
of everything else.
还要Helen带Bobby不太好
所以让我带他回家吧?
So why don't I
just take him home with me?
Just until you've had a chance
to come to terms with everything.
等你事情都处理好了再送回来
- 我今天没法面对这事 真的
I can't cope with this today.
- Pamela
Really, I can't. Pamela.
爸爸 我不过是想帮忙
Daddy, I'm just trying
to do what's best.
别这样亲爱的
Please, my dear.
You promised.
你保证过的
你说如果我表现好就答应我的啊
You said you'd see,
if I'd been good.
你不能就这么把孩子留在这
You can't just keep him here.
Tell her she can't.
告诉她不可以
Helen.
Helen
他是我的孩子
He belongs to me. He's mine.
Daddy... Daddy, please...
爸爸 求你了...
You always take her side.
你总是向着她
I'm going to telephone a taxi.
我去叫车
If Bobby's things aren't
here, ready, by the
等我回来 Bobby的东西还没准备好的话
我闹给你们看
time I get back,
there'll be hell to pay.
能给我车钱吗?
Can you give me the fare?
- 我可以送你
- 不用
I can take you home. No.
我不会跟你走的 你跟他们是一伙的
No, I'm not going anywhere with you.
You're in on it with them.
拜托了 10先令就够了
Please. Ten shillings
should cover it.
Please don't give her any money.
请别给她钱
Of course.
- 好的
Bloody fool. He thinks...
- 蠢货 他以为...
Helen. He thinks he's helping.
- Helen
- 他以为他在帮忙
You think you're helping,
but you're not.
你以为你在帮忙 你在帮倒忙
You don't know her.
你不了解她
As far as the family's concerned,
Mrs Cartwright took a sleeping pill
就家里人所知 Cartwright太太吃了安眠药
and went to bed at ten o'clock.
And the girl with the fits?
- 10点就睡了
- 另一个符合条件的姑娘呢?
Cartwright医生去上班前
Dr Cartwright took her
from Sloan House to
把她从Sloan大宅捎回了她在Florence Pard的家
her flat in Florence
Park before his rounds.
And?
还有呢?
Sir Edmund was working in his rooms
at Beaufort College.
Edmund爵士一直在Beaufort学院的办公室工作
- 他说他11点左右到家的
- 他挺有名是不是?
Says he got home about eleven.
He's someone, isn't he?
Worked with the Americans
on the bomb. Knighted for it.
和美国人研究炸弹 还授了爵位
简单说 家里没有人是有可靠不在场证明的 长官
There's not one of the family
with a solid alibi, sir.
Family? I thought it was a robbery.
调查家人? 不是说抢劫吗?
Well, his wallet's gone, sir,
certainly. But his watch...
钱包虽然不在了 长官 但是手表啊...
婚戒啊 领带夹都在
wedding ring,
tie pin, it's all here.
Not much of a robber
to leave those behind.
抢劫的话没理由不拿走这些
Adhesive plaster, sir.
He was on call last night.
橡皮膏 长官 他昨晚出诊了
Final patient he attended
was half eight. Summertown.
最后一个病人是在Summertown 他8点半出诊的
那他大老远跑去Godstow做什么?
Then what's he doing
driving all the way out to Godstow?
- 为女人奔走?
- 还有一种可能 长官
Fancy woman on the go?
There is another possibility, sir.
Given where it's happened. Oh.
考虑到凶案发生的地方
Touch of the Chase Me Charlies,
you mean?
你是说比谁跑得远啊?
- 他们没小孩吧?
- 私下约会?
No kids, have they?
An immoral rendezvous?
I should hope this case might be
resolved
我希望解决这案子的同时
不要推翻他们对他的认识
without resorting to gross slurs
against a man's character.
For heaven's sake, Dr Cartwright
was married, wasn't he?
看在老天爷的份上 Cartwright医生结婚了不是吗?
No. Helen.
别啊 Helen
你一定认为我们很无情
You must think us very heartless.
孩子的利益重于其他
One has to put the child first.
She's not fit, you see.
你看 她身体不好
If something happened...
她身体不好 万一有什么事...
When did the seizures start?
癫痫从什么时候开始的?
She was about 12,
12岁的时候
which Frank said is often the case.
Frank说这很正常
- Helen!
Helen!
Get in the taxi.
快上车
Pamela一直是个困难儿童
Pamela was always a difficult child.
她吹牛 说谎
She told tall tales.
Lies, I suppose.
She hid things.
La Gazza Ladra, we called her.
藏东西 我们叫她贼喜鹊
- 她发作的时候暴力吗?
- 力气还大得很
Was she violent in her fits?
And desperately strong.
我太太反对但是我们...
My wife was against it but we...
但是我们把她送走了
..we had her put away.
I've put him down. Hopefully
he'll just cry himself to sleep.
我让他躺下了 希望他会哭累了睡着
When was she released?
- 她什么时候出院的?
We were talking of Pamela.
- 我们在聊Pamela
天呐 每天都要谈
My God, even today.
- Helen
- 她18岁生日过后
Helen.
Just after her 18th birthday.
但是这跟我先生被枪杀有什么关系
Though, what that
has to do with my
真不明白
husband being shot,
I have no idea.
好好说话
Please.
我妈妈过世的时候 要我们保证会带Pamela回家
When Mummy was dying, she had
us promise to bring Pamela home.
Frank 解释说服药后有了奇迹般的进展
Frank explained there'd been
miraculous advances with drugs,
such that she really ought to
be able to manage on her own.
因此她应当能够自己照顾好自己
That's when she went to London?
她就是那个时候去的伦敦?
我上司说她在那里工作过
My inspector said she had a job
there.
ICI?
Frank was at St Mary's at the time.
- 帝国化学工业公司?
- Frank当时在St Mary上班
So he could look in and make sure
she was taking her tablets.
所以他会去看她 确保她有吃药
Then... um...
when he came back to Oxford,
然后他回牛津后
她就开始不接电话
telephone calls went unanswered,
letters returned unopened.
信也退回来
接着有一天就这么出现在门口
And one day she just turned up here.
成了一个抱着孩子的年轻寡妇
A young widow with a child in tow.
是的 这是...
Yes, that's um...
Frank Cartwright
..Frank Cartwright.
My husband always
looked on the bright side of things.
我丈夫总是很乐观
乐天派
Happy go lucky.
说不定这就是他引起我注意的地方吧
Perhaps that's what first drew me
to him.
Not that...
Things at home weren't always uh...
不是...家里的事总是...
你成长过程肯定不容易
It must have been difficult for you,
growing up.
我学会不提她的名字
I learnt not to mention the P-word.
And I missed her. All her...
但我想念她 她的..
Missed her terribly.
非常想她
How long was she confined?
Six years.
- 她被关了多久?
- 六年
不是疯人院
It wasn't an asylum.
人人都觉得是
People always assume.
妈妈是肯定不会同意的
Mummy would have never allowed that.
It was... very nice.
是个挺好的地方
就是一个专门给像Pamela这种人待的地方
A... A colony... for... people
like Pamela.
癫痫病人待的地方?
An epileptic colony?
是的
Yes.
- 有人在家吗?
Hello? Anyone in?
Heavy, I'd imagine,
- 提这么一大袋东西很重吧
lugging all that lot about.
- 是个煤气表
- 可以给我看下你的证件吗
Meter. Can I see some identification
if you don't mind?
好像没带 一定是忘在另一条裤子兜里了
Wouldn't you know it? Must've
left it in my other trousers.
是吗
Pity.
你看 我带着我的呢
See, I've got mine.
- 你打电话给库房了吗?
- 真抱歉 都下班了
You've rung the depot?
Out of hours, I'm afraid.
I called an emergency number
but they have no record of you.
我打了紧急联系电话 可是他们没有你的记录
文书可能还没完成
Paperwork can't have gone
through yet.
I've only been in the job
three weeks.
我才刚上班三个星期
Spencer警员会保证你的饮食的
Constable Spencer
will see you're taken
care of for a drink
and a hot meal.
抓到人啦? 我们要炫耀下才行啊
Made an arrest, then?
We'll hang the flags out.
Poor Frank.
可怜的Frank
I don't think
I was a very good wife.
- 我真不是个好妻子
I'm sure that's not the case.
- 我相信你是的
I don't think I ever loved him,
you see.
我觉得我从来没真正地爱过他
Not properly.
The way one reads about it in books.
书上是这么写的
"他把她拥进怀里 一切都变成了迷雾"
"He took her in his arms
and all became a mist."
母亲去世后
And he was kind...
他对我很好
after Mummy.
Took me out once or twice.
偶尔会带我出门
我不接受他求婚的话 有点说不过去
When he proposed,
it seemed impolite to refuse.
- 这不是唯一的理由吧
- 是吗?
There must have been more than that.
Must there?
也许如果我们有孩子的话...
Perhaps if we'd had children...
Some girls take to it, I suppose.
可能有些姑娘会习惯
Oh...
I don't want to be old and alone.
我不想孤独终老
You won't let that happen, will you?
你不会让我孤独终老吧?
Helen... 你是世界上最好的姑娘
Helen... you are the most simply
marvellous girl in the whole world.
You know I've always thought that.
Have you?
- 你知道我一直这样认为的
- 是吗?
I used to tease Frank about it.
我以前老拿这个开Frank的玩笑
我会说 "是我先遇到她的
"I saw her first," I'd say.
"你个幸运的混蛋 如果你不好好看着她
"Lucky devil, if you
don't watch out, I
shall steal her out
from under you."
"我会把她从你身边夺走的"
Will you?
你会吗?
An honest mistake, sir. That's
not how the gas board sees it.
- 这是无心之过 长官
- 燃气委员会可不这么认为
Aye-aye. The gas man cometh.
哟 这不是燃气侠嘛
I spent two hours on the telephone
last night, rectifying matters.
昨晚我在家打了两个小时的电话
At home! Mrs Bright's bridge evening
was quite ruined.
搞定这件事 Bright的桥牌之夜都给毁了
An honest working man arrested while
going about his lawful business.
一个诚实工作的人因为做份内事而被捕
It's not good enough, Thursday.
这可不太好啊 Thursday
我想你最好主动消失一下
I think you'd better
make yourself scarce.
"人为妇人所生 日子短少
"Man that is born of a woman
hath but a short time to live"
and is full of misery.
多有患难
He cometh up and is cut down
like a flower.
出来如花 又被割下
飞去如影
He fleeth as it were a shadow
不能存留
and continueth not in one stay.
这样的人你岂睁眼看他吗
And dost thou open thine eyes
upon such a one
"and bringest me into judgment
with thee?"
又叫我来受审吗?"
Monkford牧师 自行车丢失后你报案了吗?
Had you reported the bicycle stolen,
Reverend Monkford?
No, no. Someone else's need
was clearly far greater than mine.
没 没有 因为明显别人比我更需要它
When was this? Ah... gosh...
- 什么时候丢的?
- 我想想...
好几个星期前
a few weeks ago now.
我知道 我该把自行车锁上的
Yes, I should have kept it
chained up, I suppose.
It was found by the river,
at Godstow.
我们在Godstow的河边发现了它
Outside a public convenience.
在一个公共厕所的外面
Do you know the area?
No, no. Um...
- 你知道那个地方吗
- 不 不...
No, I'm afraid I don't.
我不知道那里
Have you ever met a Dr Cartwright?
Frank Cartwright.
你见过Cartwright医生吗? Frank Cartwright
He has a practice in Florence Park.
他在Florence Park有个诊所
嗯 我认识我教区里的所有医生 但是...
Well, I know all the doctors
in my parish, obviously, but erm...
that's about it.
- 我不认识他
You've an interest in science?
- 你喜欢科学?
是的
Yes.
是的 战前我在Beaufort读化学
Yes, I read chemistry at Beaufort
before the war.
我对事物的本质很感兴趣
I've kept a keen interest
in the nature of things.
事物的真面目
The truth of them.
我觉得 事物是有共通点的
Something we have in common,
I should imagine.
Well, we share a passion
for cruciverbalism, certainly.
显然我们的共通点是纵横填字游戏
Yes.
是啊
我总是对谜很上瘾
I've always had a weakness
for a puzzle.
Alas, I'm a little off my
game today.
唉 今天解填字游戏玩得不是很顺啊
你可以试试纵向11
You might want to take a look
at 11 down.
"Running over a dune is an effort."
Nine letters.
"跑向沙丘是一种努力" 9个字母
(endeavour)
Think it should help you
with the south-west quadrant.
这个应该对解右下角这块有帮助
You do seem an unlikely sort of
policeman.
你看起来不太像警察啊
If you'll forgive me.
抱歉我口快了
在研究院跟通信兵之后
Well, it's rather
where I have ended up,
by way of academe and the Signal
Corps.
我就该干这行
- 博而不精
- 通信兵?
Jack of all trades.
The Signal Corps?
你在那做什么?
Mm. What were you doing there?
密码员
I was a cipher clerk.
Cipher clerk. Indeed?
密码员是吗?
我看到你墓园里的一个碑
I noticed a grave in your churchyard.
Lady Daphne Sloan. 1903 to 1960.
Daphne Sloan女士 1903年到1960的那位
Anything to do with the Sloans
at Cumnor, would you know?
你知道她和Cumnor的Sloan家有关系吗?
是的 Sloan家族和St Eligius教堂
Yes, yes. Yes, the
Sloan family have
有诸多渊源
a long association
with St Eligius,
going back many generations.
多年前
我主持过其中一位的婚礼
I married one of them a
few years ago.
Well, performed the service,
at least.
至少 主持了仪式
Helen, would that be?
- 会是Helen吗?
Possibly.
- 可能
呃...我不太记得名字了
I'm afraid names don't erm...
You know.
另外还想问一下 星期一晚上你在哪?
As a matter of interest,
where were you Monday night?
星期一晚上?
Monday night?
Yes, I was here.
我在这里
在准备星期天的布道
Preparing... the sermon for Sunday.
It's an expository.
经文解释
马太福音 14章 第7节
St Matthew, chapter seven,
verse seven.
我想知道
I have to ask...
你是怎么找到我的
How did you find me?
排除法
Process of elimination.
There aren't that many
left-handed vicars in the diocese.
教区里并没有很多左撇子牧师
I'll see your bike's
returned as soon
我们调查完你的自行车
会立即归还的
谢谢
as we're done with it.
Thank you.
既然你帮了我
Well, seeing as you've helped me,
by way of recompense,
作为回报
"胡子被取笑后
"After beard teased..."
"惊讶的叫声会带你回家"
"..an exclamation of surprise
will bring you home."
11 letters.
11个字母
Well, it's something for you to
think about on the way back to town.
回去路上没事你可以想想
I'm sorry sir. This last
chapter seems to be taking longer.
对不起 先生 这章花的时间有点长
尽快 Denis
As soon as you can, Denis.
- 啊 我忘记拿...
- 去吧
Oh, I've left my... All right.
Sir Edmund, I wonder,
might I speak with you a moment?
Edmund爵士 有时间可以聊一聊吗
我正好要去食堂 你要一起用餐吗
I was just on my way to hall.
Perhaps you'd care to join me?
I'd be glad of your company.
That's... very kind.
- 我会很高兴与你一同用餐的
- 这...非常感谢
不用客气
Not at all.
That was Denis Bradley, wasn't it?
One of my brightest.
- 那位是Denis Bradley吗?
- 我最得意的门生之一
A rather promising young physicist,
一位非常有前途的小物理学家
and more importantly,
an accomplished transcriber.
更重要的是他是一位非常熟练的誊写员
He's been helping with my memoirs.
他在帮助我完成自传
Typing up my rather illegible
longhand. How do you know him?
把我潦草的手写打成定稿 你怎么会知道他的?
Oh, a girl he was seeing
因为他女朋友
Margaret Bell - died
suddenly last weekend.
Margaret Bell 上周末突然死了
Ah, good heavens. I'd no idea.
天呐 我完全不知道这事
可怜的孩子
Oh, poor boy.
Of course. That will explain it.
Explain what?
- 难怪 这就说得通了
- 什么说得通了?
最近他交上来的几页
Well, the latest
pages he turned in
were awash with
typographical lacunae.
有大量的打印空白
我过于苛责他了
I'm afraid I may have been a little
hard on him.
Has he ever been to Sloan House?
Once or twice.
- 他去过Sloan大宅吗?
- 一两次吧
To collect my notes and deliver
fair copy.
来拿我的笔记和送清稿
He'd have known Dr Cartwright, then.
那他应该认识Cartwright医生吧
Frank? 是啊 我想他应该在那里见过他
Frank? Yes, I suppose he would
have seen him about the place.
Please.
- 请
Thank you.
- 谢谢
Now, you must tell me.
I've rather held off asking.
有个问题我想问很久了
听说你是Lonsdale毕业的吧
But I gather you were at Lonsdale.
- 你怎么知道的
- 高级活动室里听来的
Where would you gather that?
Oh, talk in the SCR.
Oxford's a self-regarding
sort of place. Insular.
牛津可是很自我的 与世隔绝
古典人文的肄业生成了
You can't deny the novelty
of a Greats undergraduate
serving as a constable
with the city police.
一名郡警察 很新奇的事
总可以试试的
I can try.
你女儿和Cartwright医生的婚姻...
Your daughter's marriage
to Dr Cartwright...
婚姻美满吗?
Was that an altogether happy one?
我得说没有一段婚姻是完美的
Well, I'd say no marriage
is altogether happy.
但是Helen和Frank还算是挺美满的
But Helen and Frank
were happier than most.
那你和Cartwright医生的关系怎么样呢?
And your own relationship with
Dr Cartwright. How was that?
Whatever reservations
I may have had,
不管我对他有什么想法
Frank became like a son to me.
我待Frank就像儿子一般
A happy family, then?
- 快乐的一家人咯?
- 你不觉得快乐是个很主观的东西吗?
Happiness is subjective,
don't you think?
比如我吧 有荣誉 有头衔
Take me. Feted, titled...
但是... 我太太 Pamela...
..and yet... my wife, Pamela...
..and now Frank.
现在Frank又...
如果我还相信快乐的存在
我会觉得它是有争议的
I'd say it was a judgment,
if I believed in such things.
For what?
为什么?
I helped unleash a force
with the power to
我解开了一股
wipe mankind from the
face of the earth.
可以抹去人类的力量
And that troubles you?
那困扰着你吗?
A quarter of a million souls
is a lot to answer for.
二十五万人的性命足够回答这个问题了
It would seem
I'm not alone in that view.
而且看起来不单是我一个人这么认为
- 他收到这些信件多久了
- 差不多六个月
How long's this been going on?
About six months.
没有具体威胁内容吗
No specific threats as such?
没有 大多是一个字
No, a single word most of the time.
Variations on a theme.
相同的内容
"没人性的" "凶手" "杀人犯"
"Monster." "Killer." "Murderer."
To do with his war work?
和他的战争研究有关?
他是这么认为的 现在他女婿被杀...
Well, that's how he took it. But
with his son-in-law being killed...
Got the wind up, has he?
See if there's anything in it.
让他开始紧张了? 你还是去查一查吧
自行车查的怎么样了? 有进展吗?
How did you make out with that bike?
Any luck?
Yes and no. Belonged to a Reverend
Monkford. Vicar of St Eligius.
说有也可以说没有
它是St Eligius教堂牧师Monkford的
- 很好
- 他说车前阵子被偷了
Good.
He says it was stolen some time ago.
Not him that cycled down to Godstow,
then?
那就不是他骑到Godstow的咯?
他说他星期一晚上没出门 在准备布道
He says he was in Monday night,
working on a sermon.
Maybe we'll have better luck
with this gun.
说不定枪能查出点什么
Mr Bright wants the river dragged,
so I'm breaking out the gumboots.
Bright先生想打捞河底
所以我要把橡胶靴准备好
- 要我送你去吗?
- 不 不用
Do you want me to run you?
No. No.
Jakes will do. He's got a list
together of Cartwright's patients.
Jakes会送我 他有一份Cartwright病人的名单
Go through that.
See if there's any with form.
查查那个 看是否有人有犯罪记录
Particularly firearms offences.
- 特别是枪支犯罪
- 还有一件事 长官
Oh, there is one more thing, sir.
- Margaret Bell的男友 Denis Bradley
Margaret Bell's boyfriend,
Denis Bradley.
I thought we'd been over that.
- 我以为我们已经结案了
他一直在帮Edmund Sloan爵士弄他的自传
He's been helping Sir Edmund Sloan
with his memoirs,
Bradley去过Sloan大宅
so if the murder weapon
is the revolver taken
所以如果凶器真是他们家左轮手枪的话...
from Sloan House,
Bradley's been there.
他怎么知道枪在哪呢?
How would he know where to find it?
More than likely one
of the family made away with it.
看起来更像是家庭成员做的
谁都看得出他们一家是怪人
They're a rum lot
by anybody's yardstick.
噢 DeBryn医生打电话过来 要你去下停尸房
Oh, and Doctor DeBryn called.
Wants you to drop by the mortuary.
That sudden of yours. Margaret Bell.
Yes?
- Margaret Bell的那件猝死案
- 怎么了?
有趣的发现
胃里有一两颗未完全分解的药片
Interesting stomach contents. One
or two partially dissolved tablets.
Digoxin. No.
- 地高辛?
- 不是
These are of a blueish-purpley hue.
蓝紫色的
Dye had leached into
the lining of the gut, you see.
你看 颜色渗透到了肠道粘膜
你没事吧?
Do you feel all right?
You're not going to er... No.
- 你不会又要...
- 我没事
I can get you a glass of water.
- 我可以给你倒杯水
- 没事 我想听听你要说的重点
I'd sooner the point,
if it's all the same to you.
重点是 我刚拿到实验室结果
The point is, I've just had
the results back from the lab. Ah.
- 紫心片
- 安非他命?
Drinamyl. Amphetamine?
They're illegal, aren't they?
As of last year.
- 它们不是违禁药吗?
- 从去年开始禁的
Unfortunately, that doesn't mean
people have stopped taking them.
可惜人们并没有停止使用它们
我不会 也就喝一杯好酒
Not me. Like a good drink.
That's where I draw the line.
Derek不会把这种东西搞错的 长官
Derek wouldn't get mixed up
in anything like that.
他从来没惹过麻烦 他工作很努力
He's never been in any trouble.
He works hard.
前途无量 如果他努力工作的话
Got a decent future ahead of him -
if he knuckles down.
- 他是指屈服
- 你知道我什么意思了吧?
Knuckles under, he means.
See what I mean?
快去倒茶
Go and see to that tea.
No, don't trouble on my account,
Mr Clark. Go on.
- 不 不用麻烦了 Clark先生
- 快去
He's not a bad lad.
他人不坏
只是自从Ivy去世后
Just... It's been hard on him.
他很不好过
Since losing Ivy.
我承诺过她会尽力的 我说到做到了
I promised her I'd do my best,
but... a boy needs his mother,
但是...孩子需要他的母亲
all said and done.
Where do you want it?
要放哪?
Just about bust a gut carrying
that thing.
拿这东西可真不轻松
- 你为什么要她的打字机?
What do you want
with her typewriter, anyway?
- 我要确认件事
Something I want to check.
- 现在你自己打字一定很困难吧
Must be difficult typing
all this yourself now.
- 什么意思?
What does that mean?
Up until the last
two messages, the
最近两封寄给Edmund Sloan爵士的
憎恨信
hate letters sent
to Sir Edmund Sloan
were written on a Remington Model 5.
是用Remington牌5号打字机打的
Specifically,
Margaret Bell's Remington Model 5.
确切地说是Margaret Bell的打字机
What makes you think that?
- 你为什么这么认为
The E key is misaligned.
- 因为E键错位了
我想Edmund爵士的自传里也有一样的问题吧
I'd expect Sir Edmund's memoirs
to show the same anomaly.
Did Margaret type the hate mail, too,
or just the memoirs?
憎恨信也是Margaret打的吗
还是只有自传是她打的?
Just the memoirs.
只有自传
I typed out the rest of the messages
while she was taking a bath.
其他是我趁她洗澡时候打的
如果我通知学院的话 你会被开除的
If I notify the college,
you'll be sent down.
If?
如果?
You've worked hard.
Don't throw it away over nothing.
你这么努力 别因为无谓之事毁了前途
无谓之事? 我以为他也许会感受到
Nothing? I'd thought
maybe he felt some
remorse, some prick
of conscience.
悔恨和良心的责备
但是所有的自我惩罚和道歉不过是伪装
But all the hair shirt
and the mea culpa is just an act.
- 伪装?
- 他要去美国
An act? He's going to America.
America?
A fat chair at Stanford.
- 美国?
- 斯坦福大学的美差
He's taking them all with him.
Helen, Dr Cartwright, the kiddie.
他要带所有人走 Helen Cartwright医生和孩子
Only the doc wasn't too keen,
so far as I can make out.
只有医生不想去  我看的出来
Don't you get it?
你不明白吗?
They're paying him to come up
with new ways of killing people.
他们花钱雇他 要他想新方法杀人
My God, doesn't that matter to you?
我的天 那和你无关吗?
你的职责不是抓杀人犯吗?
Isn't it your job
to catch murderers?
- 你扯得有点远了
- 是吗?
You're taking it a bit far.
Am I?
You kill one person, they
lock you up and throw away the key.
杀一个人 他们会把你关起来
You kill 300,000
and they give you a knighthood.
杀30万人 他们会给你爵位
爸爸派你来监视我的是吗?
Daddy sent you to spy on me, did he?
不是 我就来看看今天你好不好
No. I just wanted to make sure
you were all right.
他们怎么说我的?
What did they say about me?
他们告诉你我被关起来过?
我对Bobby是个危险?
Did they tell you I'd been put away?
That I'm a danger to Bobby?
I'm not.
我不是
It was the first turn I've had in
over a year.
这是我一年来的第一次
It was a shock hearing about Frank
that way.
那样子知道Frank的事我也很震惊
你觉得有谁会伤害他吗?
Is there anyone you can think
of who'd want to do him any harm?
No, of course not.
没 当然没
他...他很善良
He was... kindness itself.
如果不是Frank 我可能还被关着
If it hadn't been for Frank,
I'd still be locked up.
You probably think I should be
after my last performance.
根据我上次的表现
你大概觉得我应该被关起来
They can't keep you from your son.
- 他们不能把你和你儿子分开
- 你不了解我家人
You don't know my family.
我能见他
I can see him,
visit my own son.
拜访自己的儿子
I have to pretend not to mind.
我必须要假装成不介意
Not to make a fuss.
Or they'll put me
不能一惊一乍的 不然他们会把我关起来
back inside and I
won't see him at all.
我就再也见不到他了
At least I know
he's just a bus ride away.
至少我知道他离我很近
I suppose that's some comfort.
这么想会好过点
你能陪我睡觉吗?
Will you take me to bed?
You don't need to buy me things
or tell me you love me. I just...
你不需要买东西给我 或是告诉我你爱我 我只是...
求你 就一会
Please, just for a while.
我是信得过才能来的
I'm here in a position of trust.
- 我不是你喜欢的类型
I'm not your type.
- 呃... 我该走了
Um... I should go.
别 留下 求你了
No, stay, please.
She saw the helmet and the plume.
她看到头盔和羽毛
She looked down to Camelot.
她俯视着Camelot城堡
Out flew the web, and floated wide,
织布飞散 滑行摊开
镜子从里到外都破碎了
The mirror cracked from side to side,
"诅咒是冲我来的" Shalott太太哭道
"The curse is come upon me,"
cried the Lady of Shalott.
谢谢 我会告诉他的
Thanks very much. I'll tell him.
警员对收赌执照有何执法权?
What power has a constable
re a bookmaker's permit?
He may...
他可以...
他可以要求查看持有者的受注量
He may demand production
by the holder.
相关法案?
Relevant act?
1963年票令法 第2节
Betting, Gaming and Lotteries Act
1963 Section 2.
认真点 伙计
Come on, matey.
These are the easy ones.
这些还是简单的
Try another.
再来个
Oh, what's the point?
You're the one wanted testing.
- 这有什么意义吗?
- 是你要考试
I can't keep my mind on it.
我没法把脑子用在这上面
There's something
about this Cartwright case.
Cartwright的案子总觉得不对劲
有什么东西我漏了
Something I'm missing.
There's this girl.
有个姑娘
呃 她很漂亮
Well, she's beautiful.
非常漂亮
Incredibly so.
But there's a sadness to her.
但是透着一股悲伤
Nothing left to hope for.
生无可恋
可是又坚持着
But somehow holding on.
事实上你挺正常的吧?
You're all right, actually,
aren't you?
Most of the lads have got you down
as a bit of a queer fish.
- 很多兄弟觉得你是个怪人
Have they?
- 是吗?
- 冷漠 粗鲁
- 好吧
Standoffish, rude. Right.
You've got to rub
along with people
要做好这份工作的话
in this job if you
want to get on.
你得和人好好相处
别担心 你能过的
Don't worry about this.
You'll get it.
就是一遍遍复习
Just got to keep
going over it and over it.
Till it sticks.
直到到手为止
Same again? Mm.
再来一杯?
Oh!
What did you find?
找到什么了?
- 安非他命?
Amphetamines?
That sudden death of Margaret Bell.
- 那件Margaret Bell猝死案
根据DeBryn医生所说
According to Dr DeBryn,
her heart attack was
她的心脏病多半是由安非他命引起的
most likely brought
on by amphetamines.
在沙漠里 军队会给我们苯丙胺
The army gave us Benzedrine
in the desert.
- 为了让我们保持警觉
- 是吗?
Meant to keep you alert.
Did they?
好笑的是
Funnily enough, I
found the Germans
我发现德国人完全不需要
managed that quite
nicely on their own.
Margaret Bell的案子里有个男的
There's a boy in the
Margaret Bell case, Derek
叫Derek Clark 在东Cowley邮局工作
Clark, works at the East
Cowley Post Office.
He denies it but I'd
be surprised if
虽然他否认了
但是我相信是他给Margaret提供了药物
it wasn't him who
supplied Margaret.
你觉得这个叫Clark的人从Cartwright那搞到的?
Think this Clark boy
had 'em off Cartwright?
I think it's a question
well worth putting to him.
我觉得这是个很值得问他的问题
Maybe he panicked and killed
Cartwright to cover his tracks.
说不定他一恐慌 杀了Cartwright来掩藏证据
Try the back.
试试后门
Mr Clark, Mr Clark, can you hear me?
Clark先生 Clark先生 你能听到我说话吗?
Is he alive? Mr Clark?
- 他还活着吗?
- Clark先生?
Wallace Clark在大约9点15分的时候
Wallace Clark heard the break-in
about quarter past nine
and came downstairs
to see what's what.
听到有人闯入 于是下楼查看怎么回事
估计他们就是这时候袭击他的
Which is when they jumped him.
Presumably.
- 儿子跟着下楼 遭到了同样的毒手
The lad followed on
and got the same treatment.
- 有东西丢失吗?
Much of a haul?
Morse正在那里查 长官
Morse is over there
now, sir, but at first
但是粗略看来少了800镑现金
glance it would appear
about 800 in cash.
Plus whatever bunce
in stamps, Premium
还有几打邮票 溢价债券
Bonds, postal orders, tax discs.
汇票 圆形纳税证
你说有三名凶手?
Three assailants, you said?
The wicked swines cut
two of the old boy's
这些混蛋为了让Wallace Clark开保险箱
切了他两个手指
fingers off to make
him open the safe.
The same as Kidlington and the rest?
和Kidlington那一样
How is it you came to be there?
你怎么会去那的?
我知道你已经和Hillian督察
说过抢劫的事了 Derek
I know you've already spoken to
DI Hillian from Robbery, Derek.
但是我还有其他的问题必须问你
But I need to ask you
something else.
This amphetamine business.
安非他命的事
On my father's life, sir,
用我父亲性命发誓 长官
I wouldn't have anything to do
with that sort of thing.
我和这事一点关系都没有
You gave Margaret
Bell amphetamines
是Frank Cartwright医生给你
supplied to you by
Dr Frank Cartwright.
然后你再给Margaret Bell的吧
他是谁?
Who's he?
Him.
这个人
他来过邮局 但是我不认识他
He's been in the post office
but I don't know him.
只接待过
Only to serve.
不知道他叫Cartwright
Didn't know his name was Cartwright.
但你的确去过Margaret Bell的房间
But you did go back to Margaret
Bell's room.
They were your cigarettes
in the saucer on the sill.
窗台的茶碟里有你的烟头
It was just a bit
of a kiss and a cuddle, sir.
只不过是拥抱亲吻而已 长官
She was fine when I left her.
I swear.
我走的时候她好好的 我发誓
星期一晚上你在哪
Where were you Monday night?
I was working late at the shop, sir.
我在店里为区域经理Truby先生加班 长官
For Mr Truby, the regional manager.
我们在弄季报一直弄到半夜
We were going through the
quarterlies till gone midnight.
你可以问他 他会告诉你的
You can ask him. He'll tell you.
All right, Derek. We'll be in touch.
好的Derek 我们会再联系你的
知道了
I see.
是的 是的 一定
Yes. Yes, indeed.
谢谢
Thank you.
供应商确认了
The suppliers confirm it.
Frank's been ordering
Drinamyl surplus to our
在过去的六个月里
regular requirements for
the last six months.
Frank定了超我们常量的紫心片
你们会不会搞错了?
There's no chance you could be
mistaken here?
不会的 先生
包装上发现了Cartwright的指纹
No, sir. Dr Cartwright's fingerprints
were found on the package.
I can't believe it.
我真不敢相信
Frank was... I mean,
it's just utterly out of character.
Frank...我是说 这太不像他了
请讲
Yes?
Yes. Yes, he is.
是的 是的 他在
我是Thursday
Thursday.
Uh-huh.
您能帮我认下这笔迹吗 Prentice医生
I wonder, might you identify
this handwriting, Dr Prentice?
什么时候发生的?
When was this?
- 哪个?
- 红字
Which? In the red.
When did it happen? Do you know?
你知道是什么时候发生的吗?
- 那是Frank的天书 很容易就能认出来
- 我知道了
That's Frank's scrawl.
I'd know it a mile off. I see.
写得比我还难看
It's even worse than mine.
Yeah.
It looks like he's jotted down
a call-out.
像是他上门出诊时匆匆写的
- 怎么了?
- 两个都是?
Why? Both of them?
Something I needed to clarify.
Thank you.
有些东西我需要确认下 谢谢你
We're on our way.
我们就来
谢谢你的协助 医生
我们会再联系你的 Morse
Thanks for your help, Doctor.
We'll be in touch. Morse.
长官
Sir.
Ranulph Monkford牧师
Reverend Ranulph Monkford.
Been in the parish about five years.
在这个教区已有差不多五年
Morse saw him yesterday.
It was his bike out at Godstow.
Morse昨天晚上见过他 Godstow的自行车就是他的
Who found him?
Housekeeper. A Miss Scoby.
- 谁发现他的?
- 管家 Scoby小姐
她来的时候发现
Arrived to find the
vicarage had been
牧师的住宅被搜了 Monkford失踪
turned over and
Monkford missing.
我已经做了一份初步口供
I've taken a preliminary statement.
Not himself at all yesterday,
she says.
她说昨天他很不像平时的他
Very distracted.
Kept going on about not talking.
非常心烦意乱 一直说不要说话
Not talking?
"Do not talk at meals.
- 不要说话?
- 吃饭时候不要说话
Do not talk travelling."
出门的时候不要说话
他还说了其他的 但是Scoby小姐只记得这些
There were more but those were
the ones Miss Scoby could remember.
我觉得这会不会和宗教有关
I wondered if it might be
some religious thing.
Like monks.
就像僧侣
Thank you.
谢谢 Scoby小姐
Not been right
for a couple of months, she says.
她说不正常好几个月了
Over some young bloke he found
kipping rough in the church porch.
因为他发现有年轻人躲在教堂的走廊里睡觉
就把他请进了教堂
- 然后呢
- 搞得他整晚睡不着
How's that?
Put him up for the night,
- 搞得他整晚睡不着 第二天早上被他赶走了
the next morning the
blighter's cleaned him out.
走的时候带走了他获奖的硬币收藏
Made off with his prize
coin collection.
死亡时间在昨晚8点到11点之间
Killed between
8:00 and 11:00 last night.
三枪
Three shots.
Two in the back,
which sent him off the ladder.
背后的两枪让他从梯子上摔了下来
Followed by the coup de grace
from close range.
接着是致命的近距离一枪
和杀Cartwright医生的是同一个人吗?
The same killer as Dr Cartwright?
我倾向于让专业人员来回答这个问题
I prefer to leave speculation
to the professionals.
I'll be able to speak to
any firm similarities
尸检完成后我才能肯定有
once I've completed
the postmortem.
哪些极其相似的地方
Looks like Morse was right
about a clergyman.
看起来Morse对牧师的猜测是对的
But not much else.
但也就没啥了
It transpires Dr Cartwright's
sister-in-law has a criminal record.
Cartwright医生的小姨子有犯罪记录
As even the most
cursory examination
就算是再草率的调查
of her history would
have revealed.
也能查到她有犯罪记录
她年少禁闭的时候
Juvenile assault upon
some poor orderly at
the sanatorium to which
she was confined.
攻击了疗养院里的一位护理员
Bad?
She stabbed him in the groin.
- 很严重?
- 在他腹部捅了一刀
但重点不是有多严重
But how bad it was is hardly
the point.
而是我们应该知道这件事
It should have come to light.
- 我去找他谈谈
- 不必
I'll talk to him. No.
他该闹够了
He's had enough rope.
Morse...
Someone was looking for something.
有人在这里找东西
- 假如Monkford牧师说谎
What if Reverend
Monkford was lying
about his bike being stolen?
Morse.
他的自行车不是被偷的呢?
- Morse
What if he was there
and saw Dr Cartwright's killer?
假如他在那看到了杀害Cartwright的凶手呢?
- 那为什么他不直接说出来
Then why didn't he come forward?
I don't know.
- 我不知道
也许是个他认识的人
Maybe it was someone he knew.
What if he was trying to protect
them? What if he...
会不会是他想保护他们呢? 假如他...
Look, I can see you've
got the bit between
听着 我知道你很想破案
your teeth but there's
been a development.
但是有新进展
Let's get a drink.
去喝一杯
It's not her. Maybe. Maybe not.
- 不是她
- 也许是 也许不是
The point is, you should have
checked. I didn't need to.
- 问题是你应该去查一下啊
- 不需要
为什么?
Why?
因为她是个危难中的少女?
Cos she's a damsel in distress?
When it comes to a bird
with a wing down you've a
如果有只小鸟翅膀断了 你近在咫尺却视而不见
blind spot a mile wide.
It'll be your undoing.
到时候有难的就是你
容我提醒一句
There's a child in this
being kept from its
mother in case anybody
hadn't noticed.
这件案子里有个一直不让母亲见面的孩子
If that's a blind spot,
then so be it.
如果这个是盲点的话 就当它是盲点好了
Derek Clark在说谎 长官
Derek Clark's lying, sir.
他多少牵涉其中 我知道他肯定有
He's involved somehow. I know he is.
Look, he might not have
been entirely straight
听着 他也许在Margaret Bell的案子里
没完全对我们说实话
with us about this
Margaret Bell girl,
but at the time Monkford
was being shot,
但是Monkford被枪杀的时候
Derek Clark was being
trussed up and
Derek Clark在邮局被人打到不省人事
beaten senseless at
the Post Office.
还被绑了起来
I don't know. Well, I do.
- 我不知道
- 我知道
你现在先暂时回去值勤
You're being returned
to general duties for the present.
Where's this come from? Bright?
Mr Bright.
- 这是为什么? Bright?
- Bright先生
No, it's my decision.
Best you hear it from me.
这是我的决定 最好由我亲自告诉你
Six months' time, a year, get through
your exams, we can look again.
6个月 1年 你通过考试 我们再来决定
- 那这段时间我干什么?
- 做好你的本职工作
And in the meantime?
Learn your trade.
谢谢你的酒
Thanks for the drink.
I'm a good detective.
- 我是个好警探
And a poor policeman.
- 但是个糟糕的警员
No-one can teach you the first.
Any fool can learn the second.
不是每个人都能破案
但再笨的人都能学会怎么做警员
我该知道它不是学校才对
I suppose I should have realised
it wasn't a school.
But it did look like one a little.
但从雨中看去 它的确看起来
像个小小的学校
Through the rain.
他把我留在二楼的一个房间里
He left me in a room
on the first floor,
我以为是做脑部检查
which I took for the head's study.
感觉过了好久
After what seemed the longest time,
I went to the window
to look outside.
我走到窗前向外看去
看到了爸爸 但是我没担心
And I saw Daddy,
but I wasn't worried.
Because he didn't have his umbrella.
因为他没带他的伞
我知道他去哪都带着它
And I knew
he wouldn't go anywhere without it.
And then an orderly
came outside with it.
接着有个护理员拿着伞出来给他
那时我才意识到...
And that's when I realised...
我在玻璃窗上敲了又敲
I banged and banged on the glass.
He must have heard me.
他一定听到我的声音
He must have.
他肯定听到的
But he didn't look up.
但是他没抬头
He just got in the car
and drove away.
只是上了车 开走了
三年里 我再也没见过他们
And I didn't see them again
for three years.
大家都知道你...在那攻击过一位护理员
It's come to light that
you... assaulted an orderly there.
There were some nice ones
那里有好的护理员
and some not so nice.
也有不怎么好的
A 15-year-old girl,
you can imagine...
一个15岁的姑娘 你可以想像...
如果Frank没出现 没把我带走的话
If Frank hadn't have come along
and got me out when he did...
上次走的时候我发现了这个
I found this the other evening.
为什么Cartwright写信给你?
Why was Dr Cartwright writing to you?
你经常见他
You saw him often enough.
What was it that
he had to put in a
有什么东西是他不能当面交给你
letter that he couldn't
say to your face?
而要用寄信的方式交给你
我同事认为你是谋杀嫌疑犯
My colleagues are
looking at you as a
suspect for murder. Do
you understand that?
你明白吗?
可我不这么认为 但是如果
Now, I think they're wrong
but if I'm going to
我要帮你的话 你必须要告诉我真相
help you then you have
to give me the truth.
Were you having an affair?
你是不是和他有婚外情?
Um... Pamela?
呃...Pamela?
Pamela, put your head back.
Put your head back.
Pamela 往后仰 把头往后仰
- 她怎么样了
How is she?
- 睡着了 我已经让她睡了
She's asleep. I've put her to bed.
It's good of you to call.
谢谢你打电话给我们
你先生在伦敦经常见Pamela吗 Cartwright太太?
Did your husband see much of
Pamela in London, Mrs Cartwright?
I think I said.
我想我说过了
为了确保她吃药 Frank会来看她
Frank looked in on her to make
sure she was taking her tablets.
那他们关系应该不错吧?
They would have been close, then?
不错? 我想是的
Close? Yes, I suppose.
And more than close?
比不错更进一步?
My God. You people
really are the living end.
上帝啊 你们这群人可真会说话
我甚至不屑回答
I'm not even going to dignify so
这种恶心的影射问题
disgusting an insinuation
with a response.
How does Pamela support herself?
- Pamela的生活费哪来的?
My wife left a small annuity on her.
- 我太太给她留下了一点养老金
She has no other income?
她没有其它收入?
No-one else would send her money?
No other relative or friend?
没有别人给她钱吗? 亲人或者朋友?
Gerald's family, I suppose.
Her late husband. Why do you ask?
Gerald家 我想 她的前任
你为什么这么问?
因为有天我看到她去兑现了一张邮政汇票
I saw her cashing a postal order
the other day.
But that's nothing
you'd have sent her? No.
- 但那不是你寄给她的?
- 不是
我的同事认为Pamela可能与你丈夫
Some of my colleagues
are of the opinion
Pamela is somehow
involved in the death of
以及Monkford牧师的死有关
your husband and that
of Reverend Monkford.
那会困扰你吗? 也许那刚好符合你的计划
Does that bother you at all?
Perhaps it would suit your plans.
What plans?
- 什么计划?
- 你打算什么时候告诉她你要去美国?
When did you intend to tell her
you were leaving for the US?
或者你压根就没打算告诉她?
Or perhaps you didn't intend
to tell her at all?
你准备去美国吗 Edmund爵士?
You are going to America, Sir Edmund?
爸爸?
Daddy?
- 真的吗?
Is it true?
Constable Morse is mistaken.
- Morse警员弄错了
斯坦福大学给了我工作 但我还没接受
I have had an offer for Stanford
but I haven't accepted it.
你在说谎
You're lying.
Don't you ever stop?
What's the matter with you?
你就不能收手吗? 你搞什么?
You've been returned
to general duties.
你已经调回去值勤了
What are you about,
coming round here?
你来干什么?
我觉得Pamela和她的姐夫有私情
I think Pamela was having an affair
with her brother-in-law.
You do? Then I'm obliged.
是吗? 那我有事做了
为了让Bright先生高兴高兴 我正准备找她问话
I was just going to question her
in order to keep Mr Bright happy.
I couldn't think of a motive
until now. What motive?
- 现在我找到她的动机了
- 什么动机?
情杀
Crime of passion
. Never mind it was her
她婚外情的对象可是她姐夫
brother-in-law she was
carrying on with.
Well, by that token you
should be talking to Mrs Cartwright.
那样的话你该去问Cartwright太太才是
如果你想找动机 那么去找她 妒忌
If you're looking for a motive,
speak to her. Jealousy.
因为她没有暴力
She doesn't have a
conviction for assault
或精神不稳的前科
and a history of
mental instability.
When you search the
flat, you're going
你搜房间的时候
to find a gun and
some ammunition.
会找到一把枪和一些子弹
是啊? 什么枪?
Edmund先生遗失的左轮手枪?
I will, will I? What's that,
Sir Edmund's missing revolver?
I'd have thought so.
我是这么认为的
如果我没过来的话
你打算什么时候和我提这事?
And just when were you
thinking of mentioning that exactly?
- 长官 我得告诉你...
- 不是现在 我不想听
I need to tell you... Not this time.
I don't want to hear it.
I'm warning you,
Morse, for your own
我警告你 Morse 为了你自己
sake, stay out of this case.
I mean it.
别管这个案子 我认真的
你再靠近这里一步试试
You come within a mile,
I'll see you out of the
我要你好看
nick so fast your feet
won't touch the floor.
看起来不太好啊?
Not looking too good, is it?
You won't get a match.
对不上啊
How about we let Ballistics
do their job?
让弹道专家来决定怎么样?
She steals things. I've seen her.
她偷东西 我见过
"La Gazza Ladra". The family's
pet name for her as a child.
"La Gazza Ladra" 小时候家里给她的昵称
"偷东西的喜鹊(爱收集或储藏东西的人)"
"The thieving magpie".
- 什么都说明不了
- 那说明她走了就回不来了
It doesn't mean anything.
It means she's going away for life.
No alibi, Morse. For Cartwright
or the night Monkford died.
无论是Cartwright还是Monkford死的那晚
她都没有不在场证明 Morse
Old man's sweating her now.
老头子正在审问她
Well, make sure
he takes a look at her wrists, then.
噢 那记得确认他有看她的手腕
除非我错了 她已经自杀过不止一次
Unless I'm much mistaken, she's
already tried to kill herself once.
I imagine she took the gun
intending to try again.
我想她拿了枪想再试一次
It's called reasonable doubt.
这叫合理怀疑
每周7(先令)和6(便士)
Seven and six each week.
Morse.
Morse!
Please, don't let them take Bobby!
求你 不要让他们带走Bobby
Get off me!
放开我!
Go gently.
Please don't let them take him.
- 下手轻点
- 请别让他们带走他
Morse!
Morse
Get off! Now, settle down.
- 放手!
- 好了 待好了
Morse, can you hear me?
Morse 你听得到我吗?
Operator, this is a police call.
接线生 警察
警员Morse 牛津郡警察
Detective Constable Morse,
Oxford City Police.
Warrant number 175392.
证件号175392
请帮我接Somerset大宅好吗?
Could you connect me, please,
to Somerset House.
出生 结婚和死亡日期
Births, Marriage and Deaths.
你是否可以帮我查一个人
I wonder if you can
tell me if you have a
看看他是否结婚了
marriage registered in
the following names.
Thank you.
谢谢
Oi!
抓到你了!
Here!
你被捕了 伙计
You're pinched, matey.
Turn to your left.
向左转
Strange警员抓到偷燃气表的人
Constable Strange
nicked the gas meter man.
Better get counting.
Fair few shillings in there.
最好开始数数 不少钱呢
警务工作 Morse
Police work, Morse.
我知道这不是勇士的方式
It's not Gideon's Way, I know.
But it's what gets them
up the steps.
但他们就是这么一步步走上来的
听到我们逮捕了那个盗你家燃气表的人
You'll be pleased to
hear we arrested the man
responsible for robbing
your gas meter at home.
一定很高兴吧
- 是吗 我不知道这事
- 他是个骗子 一个贼
Right. I didn't know it had been.
He was an imposter, a thief.
噢 非常感谢
Well, thanks very much.
But, you see, amongst
the spoils recovered
不过 你看
from your meter were
several rare coins.
追回的贼赃中有几个罕见的硬币
Formerly in possession of Ranulph
Monkford. Vicar of St Eligius.
之前为Ranulph Monkford所有
那个St Eligius教堂的牧师
这就是你回报恩情的方式?
A man offers you kindness
and that's how you repay him?
恩情?
Kindness?
他看到你在教会门廊露宿就把你带了进去
He found you sleeping rough
in the porch and took you in.
Well, he would say that.
他当然会这么说
不义之财 嗑药的基佬
Easy money, rolling queers.
频送秋波 找个私处
Give them the glad eye,
find somewhere private
and, before anything
happens, Bob's your uncle.
在任何事发生之前 真面目不露出来
They're not exactly going to
come running to you lot, are they?
他们可不会来找你们 不是吗?
他来干什么?
What the hell's he up to?
你最好离开 伙计
You'd better scarper, matey.
If Jakes blows upstairs
he's seen you, that'll be your lot.
如果Jakes告诉上面他看到了你 你会有麻烦
Could you do me a favour?
能帮我个忙吗?
你在找什么?
What is it you're after?
The night Monkford
was killed, someone
Monkford死的那晚
有人把这里彻底搜了个遍
gave this place a
good going over.
Think the boy who took the coins
came back?
- 你觉得那个偷硬币的男孩回来过?
- 不 我觉得是其他人
No, I'd say it was someone else.
他们应该是有目的地在找东西
I think they were looking
for something specific.
天呐
Good God.
高尔夫 奶酪和国际象棋社团?
The Golf, Cheese and Chess Society?
那他妈的究竟是什么?
What the bloody hell's that?
Prior to the police
I served in the Signal Corps.
在当警察之前我是通信兵
打仗的时候 我的指导曾在别的地方工作过
My instructor had worked at
another facility during the war.
Home to the Golf, Cheese and Chess
Society.
高尔夫 奶酪和国际象棋社团的发源地
GC&CS.
GC&CS
政府密码学学校
The Government Code and Cypher
School.
Monkford was a cryptographer.
- Monkford曾是个译码人
- 一个什么
A what?
A code-breaker.
一个解密码的人
I told him I'd been in Signals.
我告诉过他我在通信部队干过
- 我就是个傻子
I've been an idiot.
Have you?
- 是吗?
Breadcrumbs. Breadcrumbs?
- 面包屑
- 面包屑?
是啊 Hansel与Gretel去糖果屋的时候(格林童话)
When Hansel and Gretel
went to the Gingerbread House,
they left a trail
of breadcrumbs so
为了能找到回家的路
that they could find
their way home.
他们沿路留下了面包屑
- 什么面包屑?
- 纵横字谜答案的线索
What's breadcrumbs?
The answer to a crossword clue.
这是Monkford告诉我的最后一件事
It's the last thing that Monkford
said to me.
"面包屑"是他最后的护身符 以防有不测
"Breadcrumbs" was his insurance
in case something happened.
His way of letting me know
he'd leave a message.
他用他的方式告诉我他留下了信息
Morse 我刚听到小道消息
Morse, I've just heard it
on the bush telegraph.
The balloon's gone up.
Bright's on his way.
他们来了 Bright在来的路上
Morse...你在听吗
Morse... Are you listening?
If he finds you,
he'll be in his bloody element.
如果他看到你 他会怒的
你刚说什么
What did you say?
Perhaps you'd care to explain
just what it is you're doing here.
你要不要解释下你在这做什么
我认为我知道是谁杀了
Cartwright和Monkford了 长官
I think I know who killed
Cartwright and Monkford, sir.
- 认为还是知道?
- 知道
Think or know? Know.
What's this?
More threadbare legerdemain?
这算什么? 又来耍把戏了?
不妨听他说说 长官
Might as well hear him out, sir.
可我们正准备指控Pamela Walters 不是吗?
But we're about to charge
Pamela Walters, aren't we?
Every Friday, Dr Cartwright
went to the East Cowley post office
每周五Cartwright医生都会去东Cowley的邮局
寄一张十先令的邮政汇票
and had a postal order
made out to the sum of 10 shillings.
每周一Pamela Sloan会去兑那张汇票
Every Monday that order
was cashed by Pamela Sloan.
Why would it matter if he was
sending money to his sister-in-law?
如果他只是给小姨子寄钱 有什么问题?
Thank you. Three years ago
Pamela Sloan attempted suicide.
- 谢谢
- 三年前Pamela Sloan试图自杀
Frank Cartwright
had been keeping an eye on her.
她搬到伦敦后 Frank Cartwright一直有在关注她
他在紧要关头找到了她
Since she moved to London.
He found her in the nick of time.
- Pamela 不要
- 走开!
Pamela, no. Go away!
His own marriage
failing, Cartwright
他自己的婚姻正走向末路
understood Pamela's
desperation all too well.
Cartwright太懂Pamela的绝望了
两个寂寞的人在一个远离家的大城市
Two lonely people in a big city
far from home,
they looked to one another
for companionship
向彼此寻求陪伴和慰藉
and comfort.
- 他让她怀孕了
He got her pregnant.
- 我立即查了全国档案记录
I spoke to the National Registry
first thing.
There was a man called Gerald Walters
who worked at ICI
的确有一个人叫Gerald Walters的人
在帝国化学工业公司工作过并死于车祸
and he did die in a car crash
but there was no whirlwind romance
with Pamela Sloan.
但他和Pamela Sloan没有感情纠葛
No marriage.
没有结婚
他们的关系保密了两年
For two years they kept their affair
secret.
Pamela passed herself off
as a young widow
Pamela以年轻寡妇自居
and collected Cartwright's
weekly postal order.
每周去收Cartwright的汇票
- 谢谢
- 不客气
Thank you. You're welcome.
最终 有人意识到
Eventually someone realised
Dr Cartwright
was sending money to a woman
who was not his wife.
Cartwright医生在给一个不是她太太的女人寄钱
他们只是胡乱猜测
却正中红心
They fired a shot into the dark
and hit the bull's-eye.
那人威胁说他要把他知道的事
告诉Cartwright的太太
The sender threatened to reveal
what he knew to Cartwright's wife
以期得到什么好处
and sought to turn it
to their own advantage.
于是Cartwright定时给敲诈的人
Cartwright paid off
the extortioner with
a regular delivery
of amphetamines.
寄去安非他命
And the Reverend Monkford?
How do you explain his involvement?
那Monkford牧师呢?
你要怎么解释他被牵涉其中?
他刚好在现场撞见了杀Cartwright医生的人
He came upon Dr Cartwright's killer
at the scene.
不幸的是谋杀者同样认出了他
Unfortunately the murderer also
recognised the Reverend Monkford.
你或许觉得这个很有说服力 Thursday
You might find this compelling,
Thursday,
不过到现在为止我依旧认为这只是推测和虚构
but so far it seems to me nothing
but surmise and rank flummery.
如果他知道谁是凶手为什么不报案?
If he knew who the killer was,
why didn't he just come forward?
这解释了他为什么在大夏天晚上十点
And explain what he was doing
cycling to a public convenience
miles from his parish at 10 o'clock
on a summer's evening?
骑车去一间离他教区数英里远的公厕的行为?
- 你没证据
- 事实上 长官 我相信我有
You can prove none of it.
Actually, sir, I believe I can.
What are you going to do, produce
some eyewitness from thin air?
哪里来证据 凭空变出个目击者?
实际上 长官 我们有一个目击者
As a matter of fact, sir,
we do have a witness.
Monkford牧师
The Reverend Monkford.
Shall I send back to the station
for a Ouiji board?
要我回警局拿个通灵板来吗?
All right, Jakes.
够了 Jakes
他给我们留下了一条信息 它就一直在我们眼前
He's left us a message. It's been
staring us in the face all along.
什么信息?
What message?
- 赞美诗编号?
- 事实上 长官 那不是它们真正的含义
Hymn numbers? Actually, sir,
that's the last thing they are.
The first time I saw
it, I thought it odd
我第一次看到的时候
to have 17, 18, 19
following on like that.
觉得把17 18 19那样排列很奇怪
The last time I saw Monkford, he
我最后一次见Monkford的时候
他暗示我他要留一条信息
hinted he intended
to leave a message.
一条能为他辩护的信息
Something that might speak for him.
他知道如果他写下来的话
Even if he wrote down
what he knew and hid
it somewhere at home,
it might be found.
即使藏在家里 说不定也会被找到
他被杀当晚
And someone did search
the vicarage the night
he was killed looking
for exactly that.
真的有人搜了他的住处
因为担心他的安危
及真相会和他的死一起被埋葬
Fearful for his life and afraid
the truth would die with him,
Monkford将凶手的身份藏在了赞美诗编号里
Monkford concealed the killer's
identity in the hymn numbers.
Concealed?
藏?
I've since found out that Monkford
worked in cyphers during the war.
我发现Monkford曾在战争中当过解码员
你说这些圣诗编号是一种密码?
You saying these hymn numbers
are some sort of code?
Exactly, sir.
是的 长官
只是直到刚才我才找到答案
Only, I couldn't find the key
until now.
Actually it was Strange
who hit upon the answer.
其实是Strange提醒了我
Before taking the
cloth, the Reverend
在做牧师前 Monkford牧师
在Beaufort学院学习化学
read chemistry at
Beaufort College.
你能在他家的墙上找到一张化学元素周期表
You'll find a copy of the
periodic table hanging in his home.
Isn't that a list of the elements,
hydrogen, carbon, helium?
就是列有氢 碳 氦的表
行了 行了 我知道
Yes, yes, of course.
Strange 那有张黑板 你能...?
Strange, there's a blackboard there.
Could you...?
Each element is assigned a symbol.
每个元素对应着一个符号
Typically an abbreviation
of its name together
通常是它全名的缩写
它们的原子数都是独一无二的
都是一位或者两位数
with a unique one-or
two-digit atomic number.
Can you write these down
as I call them off?
我说的时候可以麻烦你写下来吗?
So, 74 gives us tungsten.
那么 74对应的是钨
17, chlorine.
17 氯
18, argon.
18 氩
19 钾
19, potassium.
这些元素拼起来就是个名字
The elements spell out a name.
TCAP?
Tucap? No, not quite, sir,
but you're on the right lines.
- Tucap?
- 不 不是 长官 不过你的方向是对的
Um, the chemical symbol for Tungsten
isn't Tu as you might expect.
钨的化学符号不是你想的Tu
而是德语Wolframite(黑钨矿)的W
It's W from the German Wolframite.
钾的符号也不是你认为的P
And Potassium isn't
P as you might
而是K 出自拉丁文Kalium
expect but K after
the Latin kalium.
Taken together they're Tungsten...
把它们放在一起 钨...
Chlorine.
氯
Argon.
氩
还有钾
And Potassium.
W-C-L-A-R-K.
Wallace Clark.
Wallace Clark
Good grief. Derek's father.
- 天呐
- Derek的父亲
But there's nothing to say
he even knew the vicar.
但他压根就不认识这个牧师啊
Ivy Clark 长官
Ivy Clark, sir.
Wallace的太太就葬在那个教区的墓地里
Wallace's wife
is buried in the churchyard.
在Daphne Sloan女士的旁边
The next plot but one
to Lady Daphne Sloan.
Reverend Monkford
performed the service.
Monkford牧师主持了葬礼
Bloody hell, matey. That's...
我的天 伙计 真是...
Elementary.
基本演绎法
我向Ivy承诺过我会好好照顾Derek
I promised Ivy
I'd take care of Derek.
Keep him on the straight.
- 请让他好好过
- Derek熟着呢 Wallace
Derek knew the ropes, Wallace.
就算因为安非他命抓了他
Even if we had pinched him
on the amphetamines,
the worst he'd have got was bound
over and a fine of 10 nicker.
他最多也就被具结然后交十镑罚款
Now he's looking at life.
现在他要在里面待一辈子
And so are you.
你也是
我本打算去和Cartwright说
I was just going to
talk to Cartwright,
tell him to leave Derek alone.
让他离Derek远点
Only, it was him, wasn't it?
还不是因为你
来问那个死去女孩的事情
Coming asking about this dead girl.
她以前就用过那些(药)
She'd taken them before.
没出过问题
No problem.
我发誓
I swear.
只有这次 太突然了
Only this time
it happened so quickly.
我无能为力
There was nothing I could do.
Girls turning up dead,
police poking round. I mean...
女孩死了 警察在周围晃悠 我是说...
我不能冒险 万一Cartwright良心发现
I couldn't risk Cartwright
getting a conscience.
What if he'd come to you?
万一他来找你们呢?
But Cartwright didn't know
who was blackmailing him.
但Cartwright不知道是谁在敲诈他啊
It was a blind drop
. He couldn't have told
没有名字 他不可能告诉我们
他提供的药品是给Derek的 因为...
us it was Derek he was
supplying because...
他不知道
he didn't know.
我不能冒险
I couldn't take the risk.
Where's the gun, Wallace?
- 枪在哪 Wallace?
- 阁楼
In the attic.
我当志愿军时候留下的纪念品
A souvenir from my Home Guard days.
Knew where you stood then.
- 我知道我在干什么
And the break-in?
- 那非法闯入呢?
The night Monkford died.
Monkford死的那晚
这不在场证明可真是够苦肉的啊
A hell of a way to give yourself
an alibi.
所以我们把整个房间都弄乱了
So we did the place over.
让它看起来像遭过抢劫
Made it look like robbery.
To give him an alibi.
为了给他一个不在场证明
为那个牧师
For the vicar.
他为Ivy做了一个完美的送行
He gave Ivy a lovely send-off.
但他看到了我
But he'd seen me.
没办法
There was nothing for it.
他做那些事只是为了让我远离麻烦
He only did any of it
to keep me out of trouble.
他永远没有时间看店
He never had much time for the shop.
- Edmund爵士在哪?
- 就在那 先生
Where's Sir Edmund?
Just through there, sir.
我已经决定接受斯坦福物理学院的教席
I've decided to accept
the chair of physics at Stanford.
我们在Frank的葬礼后走
We'll be leaving after Frank's
funeral.
Helen和我一起去
Helen will be joining me.
- 那Bobby呢
And Bobby?
- 他是我的
He belongs with me.
He belongs with his mother.
他属于他的母亲
You've no right to keep him from her.
你没有权利将他从她身边夺走
他是我的所有
He's all I've got.
她有多爱他我就有多爱他
我把他当自己的孩子
I love him every bit as much
as she does, as if he were my own.
But he's not.
- 但他不是你的
It's not fair. Why...
- 那不公平 为什么...
Why can Pamela have a child and...
为什么Pamela可以有孩子...
为什么...
What's wrong with...
Please, it's not fair.
求你 这不公平
我已经向港口还有机场签发了一封警报??
I've issued an alert
to ports and airports.
If you try to leave the country
with him, you'll be arrested.
如果你要带他一起离开这个国家的话
你会被捕
You can't do that.
- 你不能那么做
- 我可以控告你
There are charges
I could bring against you.
什么指控? 我是他的祖父
What charges? I'm his grandfather.
But not his mother.
但不是他的母亲
非法扣押14岁以下的孩童
It is felony to unlawfully detain
any child under the age of 14
并意图剥夺监护人对此孩童的所有权是重罪
with intent to deprive the parent
of the possession of such child.
违反了1861年人权法案第56节
Offences Against the Person Act 1861.
Section 56.
你打算怎么办
What will you do?
Find somewhere.
找个地方
远远的
Far away.
在他们可及范围外
Beyond their reach.
Now I've got Bobby back,
I won't do anything silly again.
现在我得回了Bobby 不会再做蠢事了
啊 谢谢
Ah, thank you.
We'll manage.
我们会没事的
不用担心
You mustn't worry.
I did love him.
我真的爱他
Frank
Frank.
那才是关键 不是吗
That's what matters, isn't it?
所有的都是
It's all that matters.
谢谢
Thank you.
我听说她要离开这里
I heard she was leaving town.
It's a good thing you done there,
Morse.
你做了件好事 Morse
I hope so.
但愿如此
Run you back to the station?
- 一起回局里?
Thanks, but I've got to get to court.
- 谢了 不过我得去法院
那个燃气表的案子
The gas meter committal.
- 噢 那个是今天啊?
- 嗯 今天下午
Oh, that's today, is it?
Mm, this afternoon.
I'm going to help Strange make sure
the case papers are in order.
我会帮Strange确保案件文件都没有问题
警务工作
Police work.
I'll see you back at the nick, then.
那一会局里见
Brought to you by
www.addic7ed.com